<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The priests routed in their front-guard of tythes. Or an answer to a paper brought in Mr. Naltons name (teacher of Leonard Fosterlane) to some of the inhabitants of that place. Intituled the dreadfull danger of sacriledge, the with-holding of tythes,&amp;c. A true copy whereof is herewith printed. By the shoemaker of Martins Legrand.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E683_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206808</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865914</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865914</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118169</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91007)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118169)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 105:E683[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The priests routed in their front-guard of tythes. Or an answer to a paper brought in Mr. Naltons name (teacher of Leonard Fosterlane) to some of the inhabitants of that place. Intituled the dreadfull danger of sacriledge, the with-holding of tythes,&amp;c. A true copy whereof is herewith printed. By the shoemaker of Martins Legrand.</title>
                  <author>Nalton, James, 1600-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Hen. Hils and are to be sold at his house in Fleet-yard, and at William Larnars living at the Black-moore near Fleet-Bridge.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P.16 ends with 'Finis', and is followed by 'The dreadfull danger of sacriledge'.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Nalton, James  The dreadfull danger of sacriledge.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou. 30th.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nalton, James, 1600-1662. --  Dreadfull danger of sacriledge.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118169:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRIESTS ROUTED IN THEIR FRONT-GUARD OF TYTHES. OR An Anſwer to a Paper brought in Mr. NALTONS name (Teacher of <hi>Leonard Foſterlane</hi>) to ſome of the Inhabitants of that place. Intituled</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The dreadfull danger of Sacriledge, the with-holding of TYTHES,</hi> &amp;c. A true Copy whereof is herewith Printed.</p>
            <p>By the SHOOMAKERS of <hi>Martins Legrand.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MICAH. 3.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thus ſaith the Lord concerning the Prophets that make my people erre, that bite with their teeth, and cry, Peace: and he that putteth not into their mouthes, they even prepare war apainst him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, behold againſt this family do I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe an evil, from which ye ſhall not remove your necks, neither ſhall ye go haughtily.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Micah 2.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Hen. Hils</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe in <hi>Fleet-yard,</hi> and at <hi>William Larnars</hi> living at the <hi>Black-moore</hi> near <hi>Fleet-Bridge.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118169:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118169:2"/>
            <head>Conſiderate Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow much mankind is engaged to his maker by thoſe rich manifeſtations of love which he hath caſt forth as strong Cords to draw the Soul un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf, we doubt not but thou art in ſome meaſure ſenſible, if thou haſt but tasted (though never ſo little) of the waters of life; And therefore we are confident thou findeſt in thy ſelf a Spirit strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moving towards ſome kind of reciprocall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement. And wherein can the love of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant more appear then in vindicating the honor of his Maſter? or wherein is the integrity of a Saint more diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then by bearing witneſs to the truths of his Saviour? who witneſſed a good Confeſſion when thereby he wrought our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. In perſuance of this duty, which indeed is the chiefeſt amongst others, we are conſtrained to ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing according to that talent of knowledge which the God of wiſdom hath given us, by way of witneſſing againſt thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations which covetouſneſs and corruption hath introduced and impoſed as heavy yokes upon the ſons of men, by which the man of Sin mightily exalts himſelf where God ſhould have his throne; neither do we conceive how we ſhould eſcape the ſame guilt that ſtained and condemned the ſlothfull ſervant, if we put not forth our strength and abilities, which God hath given us, in this ſpiritual conflict againſt ſin and error ſo
<pb facs="tcp:118169:3"/>much the more evill by how much the more it boasts it ſelf in claiming its deſcent and patronage from God. We have told thee what we are, therefore expect here no learned or flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe: but if truth meets and imbraces thee, bleſs God, we ſhall rejoice. If we come ſhort in handling the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as it requires, Remember that we get our living by the labor of our hands, this being the first ſhoo we ever made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this laſt; but we have aimed to take meaſure as exactly as we could. If any of a different judgement ſhall think fit to reply to it, we deſire he would ſet down his opinion and reaſons with that perſpicuity and modeſty as we have endeavoured to uſe in this Paper: if any ſhall uſe railing ſpeeches or unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary diverſions from the cauſe, we may juſtly conſtrue it to be a ſtrong ſign of the weakneſs thereof. But we hope the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der who loveth his own ſalvation, will be a more indifferent Judge, in things that concern the glory of his Creator.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>FAREWELL.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118169:3"/>
            <head>THE PREISTS ROUTED IN THEIR FRONT-GUARD OF TITHES.</head>
            <byline>By the <hi>Shoomakees</hi> of <hi>Martins Legrand.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE wonder what kind of Spirit poſſeſſed the Author of this Bamphlet at the writing of ſo inconſiſtent and menacing a piece as the ſame is: wherein every ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſpeaks him to be of a far different nature from what he would repreſent himſelf to the people in the Pulpit (and we are confident we miſtake him not) whileſt he ſeems with tears to compaſſionate them; And yet in paper denounces nothing but deſtruction againſt them, in caſe they will not empty their purſes into his lap, under the notion of tithes: without which (he affirms) it is as impoſſible for the Goſpel to be propagated amongſt men, as it is for a lamp to burn without oil. Truly if this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per had not come from his hands we ſhould ſcare have believed that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other had been the Author of it but a <hi>Papist,</hi> juſtifying the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his <hi>Papall Tyranny.</hi> But why ſhould he be ſo fiery at the firſt entrance? <hi>That the non-payment of Tithes is a perpetration of theft.</hi> Why would he have them put to death that refuſe it? If they are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of theft, as he alleges, then are they alſo guilty of death by our Law, though the value be far leſs then the tyths he demands. But we will take a view of his Paper and anſwer the ſame in order as it lies.</p>
            <p>Firſt he ſaies, <hi>It is a direct breach of the eighth Commandment,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118169:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Before you had indeavoured to faſten on us the infamous ſin of theft, you ought in due manner to have proved your own title to that which you ſo confidently affirm to be your due; for ſure we are, that no man can be guilty of this ſin but he that takes and retains that which properly and truly belongs unto another man: but becauſe you know your ſelf altogether unable to prove it, you are therfore willing to beg the queſtion, and take that for granted which lies on your part to prove.</p>
            <p>For firſt you ſhould prove your ſelf by the Scriptures to be a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that tyths do belong to you as incident to your Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>Both which we deny; for albeit you could prove your ſelf to be a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt (which we believe you never can) yet tyths would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the more appear to be your due, ſeeing they did only belong to another diſpenſation, as we ſhall prove anon.</p>
            <p>The Scripture you cite is <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Render therefore to all their Dues, Custome to whom Cuſtome:</hi> This Scripture is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impertinent to the thing in hand. For,</p>
            <p>If the Apoſtle in this place hath no relation to the paying of Tythes, then whoſoever denies payment of tithes can no waies be found a breaker of thoſe cuſtomes the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of. But evident it is, That the Apoſtle in this place hath no relation to paying of tythes; therefore whoſoever denies paying of tyths can no way be found breakers of the Cuſtomes here ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>The Antecedent all men will grant; The conſequent or Aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is clear from the expreſs words of the Text, for the Apoſtle here preſſeth ſubjection to civil Magiſtrates, ver. 1, 2. and in ver. 3. calls them Rulers, <hi>For Rulers are not a terror to good works, but to the evill:</hi> and in ver. 4. <hi>For he is the Miniſter of God to thee for good:</hi> and in ver. 5. <hi>wherefore ye must needs be ſubject:</hi> and in ver, 6. <hi>For this cauſe pay them tribute alſo: For they are Gods Ministers at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending continually upon this very thing,</hi> meaning this very thing of <hi>Magistracy:</hi> and in the ſeventh verſe exhorteth them to pay cuſtome to them. Now what is all this to your purpoſe, or what cuſtomes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to you from hence unleſs you can prove your ſelf a lawfull civill Magiſtrate? But becauſe you are not able ſo to do, therefore it is your great grief that you had ſo little influence upon the Magiſtrates of this Common-wealth flate. So that all things continue out of frame with you, except the Magiſtrates will become your Journey-men to do your Drudgery, by compelling all, bond and free, poor and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118169:4"/>rich to imbrace your humane inventions and impoſitions; Tis ſtrange to ſee, that whilſt you had any hopes of this, Then <hi>curſe ye Meros, curſe ye bitterly, becauſe they came not out to belp the Lord againſt the mighty;</hi> but theſe expectations being fruſtrated, then common ſenſe (we will not ſay honeſty) failed in you. For even you that had laid the foundation of the warre, and conſequently of the late Kings exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, ſeeing your ſelves diſappointed of the ends you aimed at, wheel about, and nothing would ſerve the man of ſin, cloathed with the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Presbytery, but a ſubverſion of our liberties by the reſtauration of the young Tyrant, and deſtruction of our ever honoured Parliament. Thus doth pride and filthy lucre cauſe you to ſay and and unſay, do and undo, yea, to become the common obſervation amongſt men, in reſpect of your impieties and diſſimulations,</p>
            <p>Again, you tell us that <hi>tythes are due by the laws of the land, and therefore the Miniſter hath as much right to his tythes, as the Landlord hath to his rent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, we anſwer, that as no Landlord can truly claim any title to the rent of a houſe, unleſs he hath a property in the houſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſuch a rent from the Tenant that holds it; So neither can you claim any intereſt or right unto tythes, hefore you can prove that Chriſt hath appointed Magiſtrates to force the people to pay tythes to you, as Tenants pay their rent to Landlords: for though the ſame may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be done by the civil Magiſtrate, as in times of <hi>Papacy</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy,</hi> yet the bare doing of a thing will in no wiſe juſtifie the thing to be good, unleſs it be in obedience to ſome command of God, now in force: Therefore though there werenever ſo many civil laws made for payment of tyths, yet would that no wayes avail you: for we hope your pretended Divine office, muſt have a Divine maintenance, and a Divine means to ſupport it, elſe it will follow, your office is humane; for alwaies he that hath power to appoint the office, will in prudence make proviſion for the maintenance of that office, by ſuch means as are ſuitable to the nature of it; and therefore we judge the maintenance of the Goſpel is not by ſuch hoterogeneal and miſchievous means as you would have it, then which all the ten perſecutions, did never ſo much hinder and quench the propagation of the Goſpel, as this <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quindita</hi> of tythes hath ſcandalized and diſparaged it.</p>
            <p>But we know from what ſink this water of death had its original, from no other verily, then the Conclave of <hi>Rome,</hi> by whoſe Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian power, tythes (forſooth) were appointed, in imitation of the Jewiſh law, for the maintaining Popiſh Prieſts, and ſo hath it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118169:5"/>run along, as blood in the veins, in all the Limbs of that hierarchy. So that we hope the End, <hi>viz.</hi> ſupport and maintenance of Popiſh Prieſts being removed, the Means will be alſo laid aſide: the firſt whereof, <hi>viz.</hi> the End, hath been ſo effectually accompliſhed by our preſent Magiſtrates, in the aboliſhing and ampulating one great limb of Antichriſt, the Epiſcopacy, that we have little cauſe to doubt of the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> the Means, namely, the total abolition of Tythes. And though for preſent you are permitted to have them, yet we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe that the Parliaments intentions therein, was to heighten your pride, or that you ſhould inſult over their friends: but rather out of indulgency to incourage you to peaceableneſs.</p>
            <p>And whereas you frame an objection, that tythes are Antichriſtian, and therefore not to be paid any longer. We anſwer, herein you ſpeak truer then you are aware, and ſo your own tongue is fallen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſelf. But to prove this objection falſe, you raiſe this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. That which our Saviour injoyned, is not Antichriſtian. But our Saviour enjoyned Tithes, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it is the manner of falſe <hi>teachers</hi> to couch their words and phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in dark and obſcure ſentences; So here the Major propoſition is delievered to us, to deceive us with doubtfulneſs of expreſſion: for if by the word [enjoyning] the Author means an approving of what was not then aboliſhed but in force, and that then onely to the Iews, the propoſition is true: but if by [enjoyning] he means a new inſtitution to continue in force under the Goſpel, the ſame is utterly falſe, and conſequently the Minor propoſition included therein. Again, to make it more evident that the Major is no pillar to lean upon, as to the matter in hand: Take an argument ariſing from the ſame propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thus. That which our Saviour enjoyned, is not Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. But our Saviour en oyned his Diſciples to prepare the Paſſeover, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.8. Therefore to prepare the Paſſeover is not Antichriſtian.</p>
            <p>Again, That which our Saviour enjoyned is not Antichriſtian. But our Saviour enjoyned the Apoſtles not to go into the way of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. Therefore, not to go into the way of the Gentiles is not Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian. Which argument becauſe it is not ſo eaſily apprehended, we will onely change the terms, and keep the ſenſe, and ſo preſent it to your conſideration.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever our Saviour enjoyned ought to be obſerved and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But our Saviour enjoyned the Apoſtles not to go into the way of the Gentiles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.5.</p>
            <p>Therefore not to go in the way of the Gentiles ought ſtill to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and practiſed.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118169:5"/>
            <p>How abſurd the Conſequences of theſe two Arguments are we doubt not, the judicious Reader will quickly perceive: but if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors major propoſition ſhould be granted, yet Reader obſerve, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt is not in this place about to eſtabliſh a maintenance for his Goſpel-miniſters, but reproveth the hypocriſie of the Scribes and Phariſees, in ſeeming careful to perform things of ſo ſmall account, and leaving undone thoſe things which were of greater concernment: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Iews being bound up by God under that diſpenſation, to pay tithes, it was their great ſinne to neglect it, and therefore God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts it a Robbery done to himſelf, in caſe they did neglect it. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. but what is this to the purpoſe, or the thing in hand, ſeeing it was ſpoken to the Iews onely as Iews, as appears from the words of the text compared with <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23. where you ſhall find the word [ye] relates to the Iews onely, to whom then he ſpake, <hi>ye pay tith, mint and rue, &amp;c.</hi> ſee Mat. 23.23. <hi>Woe unto you Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees hypocrites, for ye pay tyth, of mint and anniſe, and cummin, and have omitted the waightier matters of the law,</hi> ſee v. the 24. <hi>ye blind guids, for ye make clean the outſide of the cup,</hi> v. 25. now although theſe and many other Scriptures, did require an expreſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the Iews, of things under that adminiſtration, yet is this nothing at all to the Gentiles, for the maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, as being under another diſpenſation of a farre different na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>And therefore if you have any divine right to tyths, it will neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow, that you muſt have it by vertue of the ceremonial law, and conſequently have other things alſo which were then commanded, as well as tyths, you muſt have that kind of ſacrifice then in uſe, <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> a <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and an <hi>Altar</hi> too, or elſe a <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple erected, yea you muſt not be aſhamed of the imployment of a <hi>Butcher</hi> but kill the Bullocks, and Sheep, and Lambs, and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, and Tuttle Doves, and in concluſion turn Jew, and deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, and as the Apoſtle tells the <hi>Galatians,</hi> if they were <hi>circumciſed, Chriſt would profit them nothing,</hi> ſo may we ſay to you, if you go to the Leviticall Prieſthood, and would have the maintenance belonging to it, Chriſt will profit you nothing.</p>
            <p>And that we are now under another diſpenſation, we think the Author will not in expreſs words deny; but if he ſhould, the Apoſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouches it and with many arguments, clearly proves it by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chriſt and <hi>Aaron</hi> together, in as much as there aroſe another Prieſt, after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> and not called after the order
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118169:6"/>of <hi>Aaron, Heb.</hi> 7.11.15. and therefore the Scripture ſpeaks of him, as one <hi>not made after the law of a carnal commandement, but after the power of an endleſs life,</hi> Heb. 7.16. <hi>and that he continues for ever, whoſe Prieſthood, is unchangeable,</hi> v. 24. ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.20. clearly proves the change of the Prieſthood, in that, even Ieſus is made an high-prieſt for ever after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec, Heb.</hi> 7.13, 14, <hi>for he of whom theſe things are ſpoken, portaineth to another tribe, of which no man gave attendance at the altar, for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is evident our Lord ſprang out of Iudaea, of which Tribe</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſpake nothing concerning the Priesthood;</hi> whereupon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle affirms, that the Goſpel is eſtabliſhed upon <hi>better promiſes:</hi> and we may truly inferre that it hath a better means to ſupport and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate it, than money, exacted from men, under the Notion of Tithes; for proof whereof, may be added what the Author to the <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.5. ſaith, <hi>And verily, they that are of the Sons of</hi> Levi, <hi>who received the office of the Prieſt-hood, have a commandment to take tythes of the people, according to the Law:</hi> clearly implying that tythes were onely for that time, during the Leviticall Prieſt-hood. And now the <hi>Priest-hood being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the law,</hi> Heb. 7.12. For further proof whereof, take theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Argu.</hi> That which was enjoyned upon the Iews, onely for the maintaining of the Levitical Prieſt-hood, doth no wayes concern the Gentiles for maintaining of the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>But tythes were enjoyned upon the Iews, onely for the maintaining of the Levitical Prieſt-hood: Therefore doth no way concern the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</p>
            <p>The Major is granted on all hands.</p>
            <p>The Minor is clear from theſe Scriptures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.5. <hi>Num.</hi> 18.9, 10. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Argu.</hi> If Chriſt hath appointed another maintenance for his Miniſters contrary to that of tythes, then muſt tythes needs dye with that Prieſt-hood, to which it was annexed.</p>
            <p>But Chriſt hath appointed for the Miniſters of the Goſpel, another maintenance contrary to that of tythes: Therefore muſt tythes needs dye with that Prieſt-hood to which it was annexed.</p>
            <p>The Major propoſition we preſume you will not deny, the Minor is proved by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.8. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.4.7. which main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance under the Goſpel, is nothing elſe but the free gift of the people, compared with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.10, 11. 14.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118169:6"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Argu.</hi> Whoſoever bringeth in, or impoſeth a Iewiſh rite, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony or cuſtome, as an ordinance of God, doth therein deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>But he that brings in tithes for the maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel brings in a Iewiſh cuſtome, as an Ordinance of God: And conſequently, doth therein deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>The Major is clear from <hi>Galatians</hi> 5.2. The Minor is proved thus.</p>
            <p>If the paying of tythes did onely appertain to the Iews, then they that bring in tythes in the time of the Goſpel, muſt needs bring in a Iewiſh cuſtome. But the firſt is true, therefore the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Argu.</hi> Thoſe Miniſters that require a maintenance for their preaching of the Goſpel, contrary to that which Chriſt hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Goſpel, do therein deny Chriſt to raign over them. But thoſe Miniſters, who require tythes for their maintenance for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel, require a maintenance contrary to that which Chriſt hath appointed in the Goſpel: Therefore thoſe Miniſters that require tythes for their maintenance for preaching the Goſpel, do therein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſt to raign over them.</p>
            <p>Your ſecond Objection is, <hi>but we do not come to hear him, why then ſhould we pay him, ſince we have no benefit by his Ministry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this your ſelf anſwer, <hi>they that live in a pariſh where a godly Minister is ſeated, ought to hear him, for he doth the work of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 16.18. takes notice of certain perſons who had inſinuated themſelves into that Church, and with fair and gilded ſpeeches ſeduced the hearts of the ſimple, having oil in their mouths, but Gall in their hearts, and therefore the Apoſtle ver. 17. brands them with two infamous characters; firſt, that they are authors of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, diſſentions and ſcandals amongſt the Saints; ſecondly, that what ever they ſay or pretend to the contrary, <hi>they ſerve not the Lord Jeſus but their own bellies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We could wiſh the application were not ſo eaſy to be made as in truth it is, for (not to ſpeak of the Author of the <hi>Pamphlet</hi> in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) The general voice and clamour of that generation of men (that call themſelves Miniſters) is for maintenance, ſo that like the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Merchant that knows no end of his wealth, adventures through all difficulties and dangers for advancing of his eſtate, and yet never ſatisfyed; ſo are theſe men utterly deprived of all power to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118169:7"/>ſet any limits or boundaries to their inmeaſurable deſires, ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving how they may encreaſe their Benefices or relinquiſh them for better. Is not the whole world filled with obſervation of their diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and actions? ſo that men either diſpute whether their is a God that theſe men worſhip, or elſe are much diſcouraged from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any ſearch after him, to fear him and truſt in him, when thoſe that pretend to be his Miniſters do manifeſt they have ſo little confidence in him; what pains do they take! what friends do they make! what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry do they uſe to gain an augmentation a benefice, or ſome other preferment, if there be but a glimmering probability of it! So that if we compare theſe men with the Biſhops, we may truly ſay, the men indeed are changed, but not the manners, no, for they hold perfect agreement and union in preying upon the ſouls and eſtates of men, and yet ſtile themſelves <hi>Gods heritage.</hi> We have been the longer in this particular becauſe we find mention of the word <hi>Godly Minister</hi> in the anſwer to the objection, made uſe of (as we have too much cauſe to judge) to work upon the weakneſſes of thoſe to whoſe read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Pamphlet might haply come, and ſo with good words and fair ſpeeches be deceived. And therefore for Anſwer to your Anſwer, we ſay, That the word <hi>Godly Minister</hi> is oftner ſaid then proved, and tis no ſmall arrogancy in men of your profeſſion ſo frequently to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it to your ſelves, yea generally to appropriate it; and truly this Anſwer of yours wherin you would place the force of an Argument on your behalf, ſeems to us little leſs then ridiculous, for doth it follow, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Timothy</hi> did the work of an Evangeliſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. and was able to make full proof of his Miniſtery, and did do the work of the Lord, that therefore everyone that aſſumes the name or title of a Miniſter doth really do either the one or the other, namely either make full proof of his Miniſtery, or do the work of the Lord? Neither of which indeed is he in any capacity to do, not having the appointment or authority of Jeſus Chriſt thereunto. And therefore tis no marvell to ſee with what variety of luſts, covetous and ambitious affections they are toſſed to and fro; even in that calling wherein (if it were true) would be the greateſt comfort and contentment: when as for gain only they thruſt themſelves into the Prieſts Office, and that gain is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal mark they aim at, the Pampleteer is not aſhamed to juſtify and aver, by laying a greater degree of Sinfulneſs upon him that comes not with his money or maintenance to the Miniſter, than upon him that comes not to God by faith and hearing. Now whether of theſe two be the greateſt evills, I think needs not the Judgement of any ſubtile
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118169:7"/>
               <hi>Caſuist</hi> to determine. But alas what are theſe overtures, but the ſame Man of Sin working in a Myſtery, as was before the diſſolution of Monaſteries and ſuppreſſion of Popiſh Prieſts; whoſe guilt in making a trade of the word of God, and merchandize of the Souls of men, may be juſtly extenuated, being compared with this generation, who have found out a more refined and ſubtile way of beguiling. You ſay <hi>Tis a Sin for a man to withdraw his preſence, but a greater to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his Maintenance.</hi> You have we perceive pointed out your grief by the putting on of your finger; is it that which troubles you the withdrawing of maintenance? Truly we believe it, and if we did but ſend our purſes, it would be no great matter for our perſons. But how contrary the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> mind and practiſe was to yours, himſelf will tell you, who writing to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> tells them expreſly he ſought not theirs but them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14. Nevertheleſs though we ſo contend againſt Tyths as being both Jewiſh and Antichriſtian, and no way having the leaſt diſcent or countenance from the Goſpel, yet as we judge it our duty to glorify God in our bodies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. So we alſo know we ought to honour him with hur Subſtance, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.9. which we can in no reſpect do by paying of Tyths or maintaining an Antichriſtian Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>Your next objection is, <hi>But the Miniſter will not give us our due in the Sacrament.</hi> This Objection together with the Anſwer framed by your ſelf thereunto ſavours of ſuch defectiveneſs and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency to the matter in hand, that it doth in no reſpect fall under our conſideration; For we claim no due in your Sacrament, but do abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely deny both your Miniſtery and Adminiſtration. And whereas you ſay, <hi>All things muſt be done decently and in order,</hi> we grant it, but not upon ſuch terms as <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Epiſcoparians</hi> formerly, and now laſt of all <hi>Presbyterians</hi> would have it, that is, according to their ſtrained interpretations, and ridiculous conſequences; it is ſtrange to conſider how much the Scripture, from whence theſe words are taken, hath been abuſed by theſe three kinds of men, and by them wreſted to the eſtabliſhing and impoſing of abſurd Ceremonies, Jewiſh Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Heatheniſh obſervations, and ſinfull ſuperſtitions on the ſouls of men; So that it hath been a Common Anvill or Forge out of which they have forged all or a great part of their abominable inventions; And now the Author of this Pamplet is not aſhamed (we know not by what kind of <hi>Alchymy</hi>) to tranſmute this Scripture of the Apoſtles into a Mettal fit to receive the impreſſion of his Tythes, as though the Saints could not do things decently, and in order except they turn <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118169:8"/>by obſerving their ceremonies, but we are ſatisfied, that <hi>Pauls</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and yours, hold no agreement one with the other; for yours, if it were introduced, would quickly thruſt out, and ſubvert the order he requires. But the Pamphleteer being conſcious of the weakneſs of his proofs and the fallaciouſneſs of his inferences from Scripture, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends his Readers to a certain <hi>Dagon,</hi> or <hi>Idol-Treatiſe</hi> ſet forth by the Provincial Aſſembly; what to do? that poor ſouls may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with ſome good words and fair ſpeeches therein, and be made the more willing to powre out golden oblations to theſe ſacrificing Prieſts; 'Twere happy if theſe men had but ſo much prudence and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, as to begin to relinquiſh and lay aſide theſe in croaching and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing practiſes of tythes, leaſt the fire of the Lord being kindled againſt their elder brethren the Papiſts and Epiſcopiſts, conſume them alſo with the reſt, for being found treading, yea, ſporting themſelves in the ſelfe ſame pathes.</p>
            <p>In the next place you tell us, <hi>it is a ſinne of a high nature, becauſe it affronts and robs God.</hi> We anſwer, we have granted before, that when the Jews neglected their duty, in not paying their tythes, God accounted it a robbery done to himſelf: but we may ſay with <hi>Job, How forcible are right words, but what do your arguings reprove?</hi> Job 6.25. ſeeing we are no way concerned in that diſpenſation as we have proved before.</p>
            <p>Again, you tell us, <hi>that the Landlord lets his houſe the cheaper becauſe the tythes ſhould be paid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it becauſe your reaſons have no more weight in them, and becauſe you want the ſword the Word God for your defence, that you take hold of lyes, and run to them, as to a ſanctuary? Surely, the Lord hath permitted you to be infatuated, elſe ſuch aſſertions ſo repugnant to common knowledge, would never have proceeded from you: but we hope as it is an argument of your ſinking ſtare, when every rotten ſtick that lies at hand muſt be catcht hold on to ſupport it, ſo the Structure of your carnall Miniſtry, and conſequently your tythes, will ſuddenly fall by the power of the ſame breath that hath made ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a breach upon your elder ſiſters, Papacy and Prelacy.</p>
            <p>But we bluſh to repeat your next aſſertion, which affirmeth, <hi>that becauſe tythes are with-held, godly Miniſters are diſcouraged, their hands weakned, and their ſpirits broken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſe eyes are ſo dim, ar underſtanding ſo weak, as not to diſcern the vileneſs and ſenſuality of this aſſertion? what doth it more clearly intimate, then that the main and principal end of your Miniſtry, is for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118169:8"/>the belly? when as no preaching, no praying, no working, no glory to God, or good to men, would be by you practiſed, unleſs this cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed gain of money, annoint your charriot wheels; Nay, in your eyes, of ſo eſſential concernment, is the offering up of tythes to your ſhrine, that without it, the Goſpel can have no progreſs, no ſucceſs. What manner of God is this money and profit with you, which the Scripture every where ſtigmatizeth with ſuch infamous brands to diſcourge men from the love of it? and yet how highly do you advance it, as that the heavenly Goſpel cannot be preached or propagated, without ſuch earthly droſs? We bleſs God, that hath thus unvailed your hypocriſie, unmasked your diſſimulation, and expoſed you, now to be ſeen in your proper ſhape, fulfilling herein the ſame which the Apoſtle ſpake of ſuch kind of men, that their madneſs ſhould be manifeſted to all. But if for want of tythes ſuch dangerous conſequents or effects follow, as the <hi>diſcouragement of godly Ministers, the weakning of their hands, and the breaking of their ſpirits.</hi> We wonder how the Goſpel got ſuch footing in the world, as it did when no tythes were ſpoken of: Surely, in the beginning thereof, there was diſcouragement enough in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and yet, where do we find any of the Apoſtles complain for want of tythes? nay, we find <hi>Paul</hi> affirming, that he chuſed rather to get a maintenance by the work of his hands, than be burthenſome to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and yet ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>wo to me if I preach not the Goſpel.</hi> But ſee the abſurdity which follows. If not paying of tythes be a diſcouragement to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, then Chriſt who never appointed tythes, left out that which ſhould be a main incouragement to them in their work: if ſo, then he hath not been faithfull in all his houſe, which the Apoſtle affirms he was; yea, by conſequence he ſhould be a ſinner, and our faith in vain. So that you ſee how fruitful a Parent one ſin and error is in the production of a numerous off-ſpring; No, no, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle well knew the vanity and wretchedneſs of ſuch Creature-incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, and therefore he hath a better fountain to drink at, for his incouragement in the Miniſtry: (1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.13, 26.) than at the ſtanding and ſtinking pool of tythes.</p>
            <p>Neither doth <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> example help you at all, ſeeing the Iews were a National Church according to Gods inſtitution, and he King of that Nation; yet did he never require any thing at the hands of ſtrangers to that Church, of whom they ought not to take any thing, <hi>Levit.</hi> 22.25.</p>
            <p>But if paying of tythes were writ for our example, <hi>i. e.</hi> to imitate,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118169:9"/>how comes it to paſs that you circumciſe not your children, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all other ceremonies written in the law, but ſeeing you will be ſure to impoſe nothing but what ſerves ambition or to advance profit, what is the reaſon you cry not up killing of bullocks, for then you ſhould have the ſhoulder, the two cheeks and the Maw? <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.3.</p>
            <p>In your fifth reaſon, you ſay, That <hi>thoſe which pay not tythes rob their own ſouls of that Benefit they might have by ſuch a mans Miniſtery;</hi> We cannot find any rationality in this reaſon, nor can we diſcover how the Non-payment of tyths robs a man of any ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al benefit; yea rather we affirm that ſuch non-payment of tyths doth exceedingly enrich his ſoul in all heavenly bleſſings; for if God hath promiſed his ſpirit and bleſſings to his own waies and appointments onely, then he denyeth the ſame to all humane devices and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions introduced into his worſhip, whereof this of tythes is an Elder Siſter, and one of the firſt born, as we have ſhewed before; and therefore certainly God hath denyed his ſpirituall bleſſings unto tythes, and conſequently the non-payment thereof in obedinece to the mind of God doth the more richly furniſh the ſoul with ſpiritual enjoyments, by how much the more conformable a man is found to the Will of the Lord.</p>
            <p>In the ſixth place you tell us that, <hi>Non-payment of tythes cauſeth God to curſe a man in his outward estate, ſo that they turn Bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, and are aſhamed to ſhew their faces for debt.</hi> Two abſurd propoſitions are couched in this aſſertion.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That all they who become Bankrupts do not pay tyths, and therefore are curſed.</item>
               <item>2. That all that do pay tyths never turn Bankrupts, but are bleſſed.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Both which are repugnant to common knowledge and experience, and therfore falſe and need no other refutation.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, you ſay, <hi>It is a ſin againſt the Goſpell becauſe it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the progreſs and ſucceſs of it, and ſuch men do as much as in them ly to extingiſh the light by taking away the oyl that feeds it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Author doth not mutter out his words as if he were loath to be heard, but rounds it aloud in your ear, <hi>That tythes is the oyl that feeds the light of the Goſpell,</hi> In which ſmall room there lies a great maſs of abſurdity conſiſting of theſe ſix propoſitions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That tythes are the eſſential means or conſervant cauſe of the Goſpel.</item>
               <item>2. That whatſoever Miniſtery or diſpenſation, that ſhall be found without this neceſſary ſupporting means of Tyths, is not the Goſpel.</item>
               <item>3. That whoſoever with-holds Tyths doth by degrees quench the Goſpel.</item>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118169:9"/>
               <item>4. That ſuch a perſon is an unbeliever, and conſequently in a damnable condition.</item>
               <item>5. That tythes being ſo effential as aforeſaid, and ſuch pure oyle, as to make the light of the Goſpel ſhine reſplendently: that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver payes tythes, doth thereby help forward the progreſs of the Goſpel, increaſes the light thereof, is an undoubted believer, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall be aſſuredly ſaved.</item>
               <item>6. That ſeeing tythes are the oyle that preſerves the light of the Goſpel, and the Apoſtles were never made partakers of that oyle, It follows, that the Apoſtles Goſpel was as a lamp without oyle, and conſequently preached but a dark Goſpel.</item>
            </list>
            <p>To all which, there needs no other anſwer, but the conſideration of the ridiculouſneſs and abſurdity of them, take an example in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond particular, thus.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever diſpenſation is without tyths, is not the Goſpel; but the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, is a diſpenſation without tyths, yea, wherby tyths are aboliſhed. Therefore the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt is not the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Though this Argument naturally flowing from the ſaid aſſertion be very abſurd in it ſelf, yet the Concluſion being favorably interpreted may be true, if we make it thus.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt is not the Authors Goſpel; that is, wherein he believes, for if it were, ſure he would there find better oyle to fill his lamp, and feed his light, than that of tythes: now that all theſe ſix propoſitions, are directly deducible from his Aſſertion, is manifeſt, for thus is his ſimilitude.</p>
            <p>Like as oyle is eſſential for the conſervation of light in the lamp, and the light is impoſſible to be preſerved without it.</p>
            <p>So are tythes eſſential to the conſervation of the light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and the light thereof is impoſſible to be preſerved without it.</p>
            <p>Yea, that you may not ſeem to want words to expreſs your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you affirm that the perſecutors took away only the Miniſters, and their blood was the ſeed of the Church, but taking away tythes, took away the Miniſtery it ſelf, here a man may ſee by this doctrine, what manner a thing tyths is; and of what abſolute concernment, as being a foundation whereupon the Goſpel is built, ſo that if you do but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move it, or take it away, the Goſpel it ſelf falls down and breaks in peeces: could ſhameleſneſs it ſelf have broached ſuch a doctrine as this? No, but a ſpirit breathing forth blaſphemies hath avouched it. Did <hi>Julian</hi> take away tythes, (as you affirm, though we think you have little ground for ſuch an aſſertion) yet he did rather eſtabliſh the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118169:10"/>purity and ſincerity of the Goſpel (though againſt his will) then any way weaken or impair it: for if we conſider the ſtate of the Church before <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who ſeemed the greateſt benefactor in reſpect of outward things, and compare it with that which followed after, we may truly ſay according to that which hath been moſt truly obſerved; When there were wooden Chalices, there were golden Prieſts, but when there were golden Prieſts, there were wooden Chalices. So great was the change ariſing out of the worldly pomp and munificence that was conferred upon thoſe that claimed the office of the Miniſtery, that the Goſpel of Chriſt was laid aſide and buried: But when theſe large benevolences were wanting, as in primitive times (which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding were never called tythes) how ſweetly did the Goſpel flouriſh? and how quietly did the Profeſſors thereof enjoy God and themſelves, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſuffering the loſs of all? as in the ten perſecutions, rather then be found to have an eye to any worldly advancement or enjoyment: but ſince tythes got footing, the Goſpel hath heen no further eſteemed by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons contending for them, then as it hath been inſtrumental to fill their Coffers.</p>
            <p>But alas, what ſhall we ſay, covetouſneſs hath no limits leſs light, and if it be in the chariot, it drives furiouſly to ſupport worldly ſelf: but we know God hath other oyle to preſerve the light of his Goſpel withall, then tythes, the refuſe of that dark and legal adminiſtration. Neither know we any other light of the Goſpel then Jeſus Chriſt, who is the true and onely light, <hi>enlightning every one that cometh into the world, John</hi> 1.9. who we are ſure is not ſurpported by tythes.</p>
            <p n="8">8. You affirme, <hi>It is a ſin that will not be pordoned upon repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, without reſtitution,</hi> according to that of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> whoſe words (as you ſay) are, <hi>Non remittitur peccatum niſi restituatur ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum;</hi> ſurely you thought the <hi>Shoo-makers</hi> of <hi>Martins Legrand</hi> did not underſtand Latine, or elſe that they could not procure the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of it, otherwiſe you would never have wreſted <hi>Augustins</hi> words as you do the Scriptures, to a ſenſe never thought of by him, at leaſt not mentioned or recited in your own Pamphlet, for <hi>Auguſtine</hi> by the word <hi>ablatum,</hi> doth not ſignifie your tythes, as you would vainly enforce, for they were never taken away from you, neither had you ever any right to them, as we have proved before; but his meaning is, to ſhew that there can be no true repentance, where that which is by violence and unjuſtly gotten, is willingly and knowingly detained: we thought an Univerſity-man had been better read in fathers.</p>
            <p>However, if your quotation of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> had been real, and not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118169:10"/>fained, as it appears to be, for the blearing of the eyes of the ſimple, we ſhould have laid him aſide, as to the buſineſs in hand, with as much eaſe and more reaſon than you did cite him: but you are fain to make uſe of patches, for want of whole cloth, if your Scriptures had been ſtrong and ereſiſtible, why ſhould <hi>Anguſtine</hi> be brought in to take up the quarrel? but he is little beholding to you, and the more ungrateful are you to him, when you wrong him being dead.</p>
            <p n="9">9. You tell us, <hi>It is a ſin that will cry for vengeance, when the ſinner on his death bed is craving for mercy, as appears</hi> from <hi>James</hi> 5.3, 4. Your gold and your ſilver is cankered, and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſs againſt you, and ſhall eat your fleſh, as it were with fire; ye have heaped treaſure together for the laſt dayes, <hi>behold the hire of the Labourers which hove reaped down your fields, which is of you kept back by fraud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are two things obſervable.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The manifeſt perverting of the word of truth (a thing every where uſual with the Avthor of the Pamphlet) to ſuch a ſenſe as common ſenſe, may perceive to be inconfiſtent with the Apoſtles words.</item>
               <item>2. The Contradiction it contains to the former aſſertion, where the Author affirms, <hi>ſuth as refuſe to pay tythes, turn Bankrupts, and dare not ſhew their faces for debt,</hi> but here brings in the tyth-refuſers, as having heaps of gold and treaſure, ſo that the very ruſt thereof, ſhall cry for vengeance: But no marvel we meet with ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions when the Proverb ſaith, It behoveth a lyar to be a mindful; for certain it is, thoſe that abound with gold and ſilver, cannot in any kind of probability turn Bankrupts.</item>
            </list>
            <p>However, let us take the application as it is made by the Author, and conſider the inward parts of it, whether they will not caſt ſome ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour into his noſtrils.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That the Apoſtle intends this for a reproof to all ſuch as pay not tythes.</item>
               <item>2. That the non-payment of tythes is a damnable ſin, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons go to hell.</item>
               <item>3. That the Miniſters or Prieſts claiming theſe tythes, are meer hirelings, and that for money as labourers are.</item>
               <item>4. That if this hire be not paid them, they will relinquiſh and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don their Maſters ſervice, as labourers do.</item>
               <item>5. That theſe hirelings are not ſowers of ſeed, but reapers down of the corn, that is, uſe all the means they can to quench, cut down, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the flouriſhing graces of God in his Saints, by ſetting and uſing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118169:11"/>rowling ſtones of reſtraint and violence upon them.</item>
               <item>6. That there is no other conſideration inducing them to undertake their ſervice but wages and hire as it is with labourers.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But if this <hi>Diana</hi> of <hi>tythes,</hi> a <hi>Diana</hi> onely to her Prieſts, but a Hydra or a ſeven-headed monſter to the people, we ſay if it were a thing of ſuch deep concernment, of ſuch neceſſary conſequence as you would in force upon it, whence is it that it had not the honour to have a name no not ſo much as to be mentioned in all the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be by way of Abolition, as in <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.5. no not in thoſe places where the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath occaſion to exhort the Saints to part with their carnall things to them which miniſter ſpiritual things; either the Apoſtles had ſupinely forgot it, or elſe had no Commiſſion either to commend it or command it: the firſt is not like to be true, no, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Author will not affirm it; therefore the ſecond is true.</p>
            <p>Having now finiſhed our anſwer to your Iewiſh Tenet, ſet forth with a thundring tytle, and proclaimed as with the roaring of a Lyon, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing thereby to amaze and a fright the lambs of Jeſus feeding peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in the pleaſant paſtures of his word and ordinances. We pray that the Lord may ſo give us underſtanding in all things, as to keep our feet ſtedfaſt in the wayes of truth, without ſliding and falling upon the ſlippy Ice of humane inventions and ſuperſtitions, and that the ſame Lord will ſo open the eyes of the blind, and turn the hearts of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, that they may not lift up their hearts or voices againſt the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments of the moſt high, and that none may be affraid, either of the power of the fleſh on the one hand, or the roaring and threatnings of Satan in a ſpiritual diſguiſe on the other hand.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>There is likewiſe to be ſold, An anſwer to this paper here follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at <hi>William Larnars,</hi> or at <hi>Henry Hils,</hi> living at Fleet-bridge, and Fleet-yard, Intituled An Anſwer to an Outragious Out-cry for Tithes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="copy_of_pamphlet">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118169:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The dreadfull danger of</hi> Sacralidge <hi>held forth in this one Propoſition, namely,</hi> The with-holding of Tyths from a Minister that labors in the Word and Doctrine, or denying thoſe accustomed rates upon houſes, which have been paid to the Minicters ſucceſſively, time out of mind, is a great and grievous ſin, highly diſpleaſing to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, as appears by theſe Reaſons.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> BECAUSE it is a direct breach of the Eighth commandement, which ſaith, <hi>That thou ſhalt not ſteal;</hi> and directly contrary to the Rule of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Render therefore to all their dues, Cuſtome to whom Custome, &amp;c</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea Tyths are due to the Miniſter by the Law of the Land, and the Miniſter hath as legall a right to the Rates ſet upon houſes, as the Landlord hath to his Rent; Therefore to deprive the Miniſter of them is a breach, not only of Gods Law, but alſo of mans Law, and <hi>who ſo breaketh this hedge, a Serpent ſhall bite him,</hi> Eccleſs. 10.8.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Object. <hi>But tyths are antichriſtian, and therefore not to be paid any longer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a falſe opinion, as appears by this Argument; That which our Savior enjoyned, is not Antichriſtian. But our Savior enjoined Tyths, Luke 11.42. <hi>Ye tyth Mint and Rue, and all manner of Herbs, and paſſe over Judgement and the Love of God, Theſe ought ye to have done;</hi> that is, ye ought to pay Tyths, Therefore they are not Antichriſtian.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obj. <hi>But we do not come to hear him, why then ſhould we pay him, ſince we have no benefit by his Miniſtery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If thou live in a Pariſh where a godly Miniſter is ſeated, thou art bound to hear him, for he worketh <hi>the work of the Lord, as well as thoſe of greater parts,</hi> See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.10. If thou do not hear him, nor pay him, thou addeſt ſin to ſin; for firſt it is a ſin to withdraw thy preſence, and then it is another, yea a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118169:12"/>greater ſin to withdraw his maintenance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Object. <hi>But the Miniſter will not give us our Due in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, therefore we may juſtly deny him his due.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, The Sacrament is not due to all, but only to thoſe that come in a regular way, according to the order of the Goſpel; for all things muſt be done decently and in order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.40. Now the order of the Goſpel is this, that the power of examining thoſe that are admitted to the Lords Supper belongs not to the Miniſter alone, nor to the Miniſter with the whole congregation, but to the Miniſter and ruling Elders, as is undeniably proved by that ſingular Treatiſe ſet forth by the Provincial aſſembly, called <hi>The Vindication of the Presbyterion Government,</hi> pag. 70, 71. Secondly, the Sacrament is not due to thoſe that live in any ſcandalous ſin; but theft, or rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of God is a ſcandalous ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin of a high nature, becauſe it affronts God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Will a man rob God? Yet ye have robbed me. But ye ſay, wherein have we roobed thee? in Tyths and Offerings.</hi> To rob a man by the high way, doth deſerve death; to rob a King of his Plate and Jewels, deſerves a tormenting death; but to rob the King of Glory, deſerves the fire of hell.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a complicated ſin, wherin fraud or cheating is added to theft: for the Landlord lets his houſe to the Tenant at a lower rate, upon this account, namely that he ſhall pay the duties to the Miniſter; as for example, if the houſe be worth 21 l: <hi>per annum,</hi> The Landlord lets it for 20 l. <hi>per annum,</hi> on purpoſe that the Tenant may (perhaps) pay twenty ſhillings a year to the Miniſter. The Tenant notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding paies nothing, but keeps it back from the Miniſter by fraud, and puts the Landlords money in his pocket. Here is fraud with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin, whereby godly Miniſters are diſcouraged in their work, their hands weakned, and their ſpirits broken, ſo that they cannot go on in their Miniſtery with <hi>joy, but with grief;</hi> This is directly contrary to the practiſe of that godly King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> (whoſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is written for our learning, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4.) for it is teſtified of him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.4. <hi>That he commanded the People that dwelt in Jeruſalem, to give the portion of the Priests and Levites, that they might be encouraged in the Law of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin wherin &amp; wherby the Defrauder robs his own Soul of that ſpiritual benefit and advantage which he might get by ſuch a mans
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118169:12"/>Miniſtery; for it is juſt with God to ſay to ſuch a man, thou withdraweſt maintenance from my ſervant, and I will withdraw my bleſſing from my own ordinance, ſo that the word preached (by whomſoever it be diſpenſed) ſhall do thee no good at all, but rather it ſhall be a ſavor of death, to thy own condemnation. Thy ſoul ſhall never thrive or proſper by any Sermon that thou heareſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin that provokes God to curſe a man in his outward eſtate and trading, as appears by that forenamed place, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Ye are curſed with a curſe, for ye have robbed me;</hi> it is uſual with God to pay ſinners with their own coin; they rob God in tyths, and God robs them of their trade &amp; livelihood; they grudge the Miniſters a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and God grudgeth them even bread for their Families, ſo that they uſually turn bankrupts, or are ſo much in debt, that they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to ſhew their faces.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin againſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe it hinders the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs and ſucceſs of it, for ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> much as in them lies to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh the light, by taking away the oil that feeds it, it is obſerved in that excellent book <hi>Vindic. Presb. Gov. pag.</hi> 81, that <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, that curſed enemy of Chriſt and his Goſpel, did by taking away tyths do more miſchief to the Church of God, than all the perſecuting Emperors that were before him: for the Perſecutors took away only the Miniſters (and their blood was the ſeed of the Church) but taking away tyths took away the Miniſtery it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin will not be pardoned upon repentance, unleſs there be a reſtitution as well as repentance, accordiog to that of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine, Nonremittitur peccatum, uiſi reſtituatur ablatum,</hi> Thy ſin ſhall not be pardoned, unleſs that which thou witholdeſt unjuſtly, be reſtored.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin that will cry for vengeance, when the ſinner on his death-bed is crying for mercy; as appears by that remarkable Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.3, 4. <hi>Your gold and ſilver is cankered. and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſs against, and ſhall eat your fleſh as it were with fire; Ye have heaped Treaſure</hi> (that's of wrath) <hi>together for the laſt daies. Behold the hire of the Laborers which have reaped down your fields which is of you kept back by fraud crieth; and the cries of them which have reaped are entered into the years of the Lord of Sabbath.</hi> Now if the hire of the Laborers in mens Vineyard, kept back by fraud crieth; how dreadful will the cry be of the hire of <hi>Gods</hi> Laborers in <hi>Gods</hi> Vineyard, kept back by robbers &amp; defrauders? I tremble to think of it.</p>
            <p>Conſider what hath been preſented unto you in this paper, and the Lord give ye underſtanding in all things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
